<samples>
<sample><p n="ENG192005652">Gerald was gradually overcome with a revulsion of loathing for Loerke. He did not take the man seriously, he despised him merely, except as he felt in Gudrun’s veins the influence of the little creature. It was this that drove Gerald wild, the feeling in Gudrun’s veins of Loerke’s presence, Loerke’s being, flowing dominant through her.</p>
<p n="ENG192005653">“What makes you so smitten with that little vermin?” he asked, really puzzled. For he, man-like, could not see anything attractive or important at all in Loerke. Gerald expected to find some handsomeness or nobleness, to account for a woman’s subjection. But he saw none here, only an insect-like repulsiveness.</p>
<p n="ENG192005654">Gudrun flushed deeply. It was these attacks she would never forgive.</p>
<p n="ENG192005655">“What do you mean?” she replied. “My God, what a mercy I am not married to you!”</p>
<p n="ENG192005656">Her voice of flouting and contempt scotched him. He was brought up short. But he recovered himself.</p>
<p n="ENG192005657">“Tell me, only tell me,” he reiterated in a dangerous narrowed voice—“tell me what it is that fascinates you in him.”</p>
<p n="ENG192005658">“I am not fascinated,” she said, with cold repelling innocence.</p>
<p n="ENG192005659">“Yes, you are. You are fascinated by that little dry snake, like a bird gaping ready to fall down its throat.”</p>
<p n="ENG192005660">She looked at him with black fury.</p>
<p n="ENG192005661">“I don’t choose to be discussed by you,” she said.</p>
<p n="ENG192005662">“It doesn’t matter whether you choose or not,” he replied, “that doesn’t alter the fact that you are ready to fall down and kiss the feet of that little insect. And I don’t want to prevent you—do it, fall down and kiss his feet. But I want to know, what it is that fascinates you—what is it?”</p>
<p n="ENG192005663">She was silent, suffused with black rage.</p>
<p n="ENG192005664">“How dare you come brow-beating me,” she cried, “how dare you, you little squire, you bully. What right have you over me, do you think?”</p>
<p n="ENG192005665">His face was white and gleaming, she knew by the light in his eyes that she was in his power—the wolf. And because she was in his power, she hated him with a power that she wondered did not kill him. In her will she killed him as he stood, effaced him.</p>
<p n="ENG192005666">“It is not a question of right,” said Gerald, sitting down on a chair. She watched the change in his body. She saw his clenched, mechanical body moving there like an obsession. Her hatred of him was tinged with fatal contempt.</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG192005710">There was a pause.</p>
<p n="ENG192005711">“Yes, I am surprised,” he said at length. “The English, I thought they were so—cold. And what do you think to do when you leave here?”</p>
<p n="ENG192005712">“What do I think to do?” she repeated.</p>
<p n="ENG192005713">“Yes. You cannot go back to the teaching. No—” he shrugged his shoulders—“that is impossible. Leave that to the canaille who can do nothing else. You, for your part—you know, you are a remarkable woman, eine seltsame Frau. Why deny it—why make any question of it? You are an extraordinary woman, why should you follow the ordinary course, the ordinary life?”</p>
<p n="ENG192005714">Gudrun sat looking at her hands, flushed. She was pleased that he said, so simply, that she was a remarkable woman. He would not say that to flatter her—he was far too self-opinionated and objective by nature. He said it as he would say a piece of sculpture was remarkable, because he knew it was so.</p>
<p n="ENG192005715">And it gratified her to hear it from him. Other people had such a passion to make everything of one degree, of one pattern. In England it was chic to be perfectly ordinary. And it was a relief to her to be acknowledged extraordinary. Then she need not fret about the common standards.</p>
<p n="ENG192005716">“You see,” she said, “I have no money whatsoever.”</p>
<p n="ENG192005717">“Ach, money!” he cried, lifting his shoulders. “When one is grown up, money is lying about at one’s service. It is only when one is young that it is rare. Take no thought for money—that always lies to hand.”</p>
<p n="ENG192005718">“Does it?” she said, laughing.</p>
<p n="ENG192005719">“Always. The Gerald will give you a sum, if you ask him for it—”</p>
<p n="ENG192005720">She flushed deeply.</p>
<p n="ENG192005721">“I will ask anybody else,” she said, with some difficulty—“but not him.”</p>
<p n="ENG192005722">Loerke looked closely at her.</p>
<p n="ENG192005723">“Good,” he said. “Then let it be somebody else. Only don’t go back to that England, that school. No, that is stupid.”</p>
<p n="ENG192005724">Again there was a pause. He was afraid to ask her outright to go with him, he was not even quite sure he wanted her; and she was afraid to be asked. He begrudged his own isolation, was very chary of sharing his life, even for a day.</p>
<p n="ENG192005725">“The only other place I know is Paris,” she said, “and I can’t stand that.”</p>
<p n="ENG192005726">She looked with her wide, steady eyes full at Loerke. He lowered his head and averted his face.</p>
<p n="ENG192005727">“Paris, no!” he said. “Between the réligion d’amour, and the latest ’ism, and the new turning to Jesus, one had better ride on a carrousel all day. But come to Dresden. I have a studio there—I can give you work,—oh, that would be easy enough. I haven’t seen any of your things, but I believe in you. Come to Dresden—that is a fine town to be in, and as good a life as you can expect of a town. You have everything there, without the foolishness of Paris or the beer of Munich.”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG192003622">“Yes, but I shall stay with Palestra. It is quite comfortable.”</p>
<p n="ENG192003623">“What takes you to Florence?”</p>
<p n="ENG192003624">“I don’t know,” said Hermione slowly. Then she looked at him with her slow, heavy gaze. “Barnes is starting his school of æsthetics, and Olandese is going to give a set of discourses on the Italian national policy—”</p>
<p n="ENG192003625">“Both rubbish,” he said.</p>
<p n="ENG192003626">“No, I don’t think so,” said Hermione.</p>
<p n="ENG192003627">“Which do you admire, then?”</p>
<p n="ENG192003628">“I admire both. Barnes is a pioneer. And then I am interested in Italy, in her coming to national consciousness.”</p>
<p n="ENG192003629">“I wish she’d come to something different from national consciousness, then,” said Birkin; “especially as it only means a sort of commercial-industrial consciousness. I hate Italy and her national rant. And I think Barnes is an amateur.”</p>
<p n="ENG192003630">Hermione was silent for some moments, in a state of hostility. But yet, she had got Birkin back again into her world! How subtle her influence was, she seemed to start his irritable attention into her direction exclusively, in one minute. He was her creature.</p>
<p n="ENG192003631">“No,” she said, “you are wrong.” Then a sort of tension came over her, she raised her face like the pythoness inspired with oracles, and went on, in rhapsodic manner: “Il Sandro mi scrive che ha accolto il più grande entusiasmo, tutti i giovani, e fanciulle e ragazzi, sono tutti—” She went on in Italian, as if, in thinking of the Italians she thought in their language.</p>
<p n="ENG192003632">He listened with a shade of distaste to her rhapsody, then he said:</p>
<p n="ENG192003633">“For all that, I don’t like it. Their nationalism is just industrialism—that and a shallow jealousy I detest so much.”</p>
<p n="ENG192003634">“I think you are wrong—I think you are wrong—” said Hermione. “It seems to me purely spontaneous and beautiful, the modern Italian’s passion, for it is a passion, for Italy, l’Italia—”</p>
<p n="ENG192003635">“Do you know Italy well?” Ursula asked of Hermione. Hermione hated to be broken in upon in this manner. Yet she answered mildly:</p>
<p n="ENG192003636">“Yes, pretty well. I spent several years of my girlhood there, with my mother. My mother died in Florence.”</p>
<p n="ENG192003637">“Oh.”</p>
<p n="ENG192003638">There was a pause, painful to Ursula and to Birkin. Hermione however seemed abstracted and calm. Birkin was white, his eyes glowed as if he were in a fever, he was far too over-wrought. How Ursula suffered in this tense atmosphere of strained wills! Her head seemed bound round by iron bands.</p>
<p n="ENG192003639">Birkin rang the bell for tea. They could not wait for Gudrun any longer. When the door was opened, the cat walked in.</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG19200656">Birkin watched him almost angrily.</p>
<p n="ENG19200657">“You are a born unbeliever,” he said.</p>
<p n="ENG19200658">“I only feel what I feel,” said Gerald. And he looked again at Birkin almost sardonically, with his blue, manly, sharp-lighted eyes. Birkin’s eyes were at the moment full of anger. But swiftly they became troubled, doubtful, then full of a warm, rich affectionateness and laughter.</p>
<p n="ENG19200659">“It troubles me very much, Gerald,” he said, wrinkling his brows.</p>
<p n="ENG19200660">“I can see it does,” said Gerald, uncovering his mouth in a manly, quick, soldierly laugh.</p>
<p n="ENG19200661">Gerald was held unconsciously by the other man. He wanted to be near him, he wanted to be within his sphere of influence. There was something very congenial to him in Birkin. But yet, beyond this, he did not take much notice. He felt that he, himself, Gerald, had harder and more durable truths than any the other man knew. He felt himself older, more knowing. It was the quick-changing warmth and venality and brilliant warm utterance he loved in his friend. It was the rich play of words and quick interchange of feelings he enjoyed. The real content of the words he never really considered: he himself knew better.</p>
<p n="ENG19200662">Birkin knew this. He knew that Gerald wanted to be fond of him without taking him seriously. And this made him go hard and cold. As the train ran on, he sat looking at the land, and Gerald fell away, became as nothing to him.</p>
<p n="ENG19200663">Birkin looked at the land, at the evening, and was thinking: “Well, if mankind is destroyed, if our race is destroyed like Sodom, and there is this beautiful evening with the luminous land and trees, I am satisfied. That which informs it all is there, and can never be lost. After all, what is mankind but just one expression of the incomprehensible. And if mankind passes away, it will only mean that this particular expression is completed and done. That which is expressed, and that which is to be expressed, cannot be diminished. There it is, in the shining evening. Let mankind pass away—time it did. The creative utterances will not cease, they will only be there. Humanity doesn’t embody the utterance of the incomprehensible any more. Humanity is a dead letter. There will be a new embodiment, in a new way. Let humanity disappear as quick as possible.”</p>
<p n="ENG19200664">Gerald interrupted him by asking,</p>
<p n="ENG19200665">“Where are you staying in London?”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG192001560">“We could hardly pretend to be strangers, could we?”</p>
<p n="ENG192001561">There was a stubborn pause.</p>
<p n="ENG192001562">“But isn’t that a half-measure?” asked Ursula at length.</p>
<p n="ENG192001563">“I don’t think so,” he said. “You’ll be able to tell me if it is.”</p>
<p n="ENG192001564">Again there was a pause of some minutes’ duration. He was thinking.</p>
<p n="ENG192001565">“One must throw everything away, everything—let everything go, to get the one last thing one wants,” he said.</p>
<p n="ENG192001566">“What thing?” she asked in challenge.</p>
<p n="ENG192001567">“I don’t know—freedom together,” he said.</p>
<p n="ENG192001568">She had wanted him to say ‘love.’</p>
<p n="ENG192001569">There was heard a loud barking of the dogs below. He seemed disturbed by it. She did not notice. Only she thought he seemed uneasy.</p>
<p n="ENG192001570">“As a matter of fact,” he said, in rather a small voice, “I believe that is Hermione come now, with Gerald Crich. She wanted to see the rooms before they are furnished.”</p>
<p n="ENG192001571">“I know,” said Ursula. “She will superintend the furnishing for you.”</p>
<p n="ENG192001572">“Probably. Does it matter?”</p>
<p n="ENG192001573">“Oh no, I should think not,” said Ursula. “Though personally, I can’t bear her. I think she is a lie, if you like, you who are always talking about lies.” Then she ruminated for a moment, when she broke out: “Yes, and I do mind if she furnishes your rooms—I do mind. I mind that you keep her hanging on at all.”</p>
<p n="ENG192001574">He was silent now, frowning.</p>
<p n="ENG192001575">“Perhaps,” he said. “I don’t want her to furnish the rooms here—and I don’t keep her hanging on. Only, I needn’t be churlish to her, need I? At any rate, I shall have to go down and see them now. You’ll come, won’t you?”</p>
<p n="ENG192001576">“I don’t think so,” she said coldly and irresolutely.</p>
<p n="ENG192001577">“Won’t you? Yes do. Come and see the rooms as well. Do come.”</p>
<p n="ENG192001578">He set off down the bank, and she went unwillingly with him. Yet she would not have stayed away, either.</p>
<p n="ENG192001579">“We know each other well, you and I, already,” he said. She did not answer.</p>
<p n="ENG192001580">In the large darkish kitchen of the mill, the labourer’s wife was talking shrilly to Hermione and Gerald, who stood, he in white and she in a glistening bluish foulard, strangely luminous in the dusk of the room; whilst from the cages on the walls, a dozen or more canaries sang at the top of their voices. The cages were all placed round a small square window at the back, where the sunshine came in, a beautiful beam, filtering through green leaves of a tree. The voice of Mrs Salmon shrilled against the noise of the birds, which rose ever more wild and triumphant, and the woman’s voice went up and up against them, and the birds replied with wild animation.</p>
</sample>
</samples>
