<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<samples n="ENG19090">
<sample><p n="ENG19090793">“I'm awfully sorry you don't like the people here,” said Roger, perplexed. “I dare say they're all stupids.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090794">“That wouldn't matter—if they behaved decently,” said Daphne, flushing.</p>
<p n="ENG19090795">“I suppose that means—if I behaved decently!” cried Roger, turning upon her.</p>
<p n="ENG19090796">Daphne faced him, her head in air, her small foot beating the ground, in a trick it had.</p>
<p n="ENG19090797">“Well, I'm not likely to forget the Brendon ball, am I?”</p>
<p n="ENG19090798">Roger's look changed.</p>
<p n="ENG19090799">“I meant no harm, and you know I didn't,” he said sulkily.</p>
<p n="ENG19090800">“Oh, no, you only made a laughing-stock of me!” Daphne turned on her heel. Suddenly she felt herself roughly caught in Roger's arms.</p>
<p n="ENG19090801">“Daphne, what is the matter? Why can't we be happy together?”</p>
<p n="ENG19090802">“Ask yourself,” she said, trying to extricate herself, and not succeeding. “I don't like the people here, and they don't like me. But as you seem to enjoy flirting with Mrs. Fairmile, there's one person satisfied.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090803">Roger laughed—not agreeably. “I shall soon think, Daphne, that somebody's ‘put a spell on you,’ as my old nurse used to say. I wish I knew what I could do to break it.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090804">She lay passive in his arms a moment, and then he felt a shiver run through her, and saw that she was crying. He held her close to him, kissing and comforting her, while his own eyes were wet. What her emotion meant, or his own, he could not have told clearly; but it was a moment for both of healing, of impulsive return, the one to the other, unspoken penitence on her side, a hidden self-blame on his. She clung to him fiercely, courting the pressure of his arms, the warm contact of his youth; while, in his inner mind, he renounced with energy the temptress Chloe and all her works, vowing to himself that he would give Daphne no cause, no pretext even, for jealousy, and would bear it patiently if she were still unjust and tormenting.</p>
<p n="ENG19090805">“Where have you been all day?” said Daphne at last, disengaging herself, and brushing the tears away from her eyes—a little angrily, as though she were ashamed of them.</p>
<p n="ENG19090806">“I told you this morning. I had a run with the Stoneshire hounds.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090807">“Whom did you meet there?”</p>
<p n="ENG19090808">“Oh, various old acquaintances. Nobody amusing.” He gave two or three names, his conscience pricking him. Somehow, at that moment, it seemed impossible to mention Chloe Fairmile.</p>
<p n="ENG19090809">About eleven o'clock that night, Daphne and Lady Barnes having just gone upstairs, Roger and a local Colonel of Volunteers who was dining and spending the night at Heston, were in the smoking-room. Colonel Williams had come over to discuss Volunteer prospects in the neighbourhood, and had been delighted to find in the grandson of his old friend Oliver Trescoe—a young fellow whom he and others had too readily regarded as given over to luxury and soft living—signs of the old public spirit, the traditional manliness of the family. The two men were talking with great cordiality, when the sound of a dogcart driving up to the front door disturbed them.</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG19090899">He looked at her intently, his lips twitching a little. Daphne came nearer.</p>
<p n="ENG19090900">“It must be something you want very badly—something you don't want other people to see—something you're ashamed of!—or you wouldn't be searching for it at this time of night.” She raised her eyes, still with the same strange yet flaming quiet, from the littered floor to his face. Then suddenly glancing again at the scattered papers—“That's your handwriting!—they're your letters!—letters to Mrs. Fairmile!”</p>
<p n="ENG19090901">“Well, and what do you make of that?” cried Roger, half wroth, half inclined to laugh. “If you want to know, they are the letters I wrote to Chloe Fairmile; and I, like a careless beast, never destroyed them, and they were stuffed away here. I have long meant to get at them and burn them, and as you turned me out to-night—”</p>
<p n="ENG19090902">“What is that letter in your hand?” exclaimed Daphne, interrupting him.</p>
<p n="ENG19090903">“Oh, that has nothing to do with you—or me—” he said, hastily making a movement to put it in his coat pocket. But in a second, Daphne, with a cry, had thrown herself upon him, to his intense amazement, wrestling with him, in a wild excitement. And as she did so, a thin woman, with frightened eyes, in a nurse's dress, came quickly into the room, as though Daphne's cry had signalled to her. She was behind Roger, and he was not aware of her approach.</p>
<p n="ENG19090904">“Daphne, don't be such a little fool!” he said indignantly, holding her off with one hand, determined not to give her the letter.</p>
<p n="ENG19090905">Then, all in a moment—without, as it seemed to him, any but the mildest defensive action on his part—Daphne stumbled and fell.</p>
<p n="ENG19090906">“Daphne!—I say!—”</p>
<p n="ENG19090907">He was stooping over her in great distress to lift her up, when he felt himself vehemently put aside by a woman's hand.</p>
<p n="ENG19090908">“You ought to be ashamed of yourself, sir! Let me go to her.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090909">He turned in bewilderment. “Miss Farmer! What on earth are you doing here?”</p>
<p n="ENG19090910">But in his astonishment he had given way to her, and he fell back pale and frowning, while, without replying, she lifted Daphne— who had a cut on her forehead and was half fainting—from the ground.</p>
<p n="ENG19090911">“Don't come near her, sir!” said the nurse, again warding him off. “You have done quite enough. Let me attend to her.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090912">“You imagine that was my doing?” said Roger grimly. “Let me assure you it was nothing of the kind. And pray, were you listening at the door?”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG19090413">“She puts you down so!” cried that lady, making gestures with the paper-knife she had just been employing on the pages of a Mudie book. “If I tell her that something or other—it doesn't matter what—cost at least a great deal of money, she has a way of smiling at you that is positively insulting! She doesn't trouble to argue; she begins to laugh, and raises her eyebrows. I—I always feel as if she had struck me in the face! I know I oughtn't to speak like this; I hadn't meant to do it, especially to a country-woman of hers, as you are.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090414">“Am I?” said Elsie, in a puzzled voice.</p>
<p n="ENG19090415">Lady Barnes opened her eyes in astonishment.</p>
<p n="ENG19090416">“I meant”—the explanation was hurried—“I thought—Mrs. Barnes was a South American? Her mother was Spanish, of course; you see it in Daphne.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090417">“Yes; in her wonderful eyes,” said Mrs. French warmly; “and her grace—isn't she graceful! My husband says she moves like a sea-wave. She has given her eyes to the child.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090418">“Ah! and other things too, I'm afraid!” cried Lady Barnes, carried away. “But here is the baby.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090419">For the sounds of a childish voice were heard echoing in the domed hall outside. Small feet came pattering, and the drawing-room door was burst open by Roger Barnes, holding a little girl of nearly two and a half by the hand.</p>
<p n="ENG19090420">Lady Barnes composed herself. It is necessary to smile at children, and she endeavoured to satisfy her own sense of it.</p>
<p n="ENG19090421">“Come in, Beatty; come and kiss granny!” And Lady Barnes held out her arms.</p>
<p n="ENG19090422">But the child stood still, surveyed her grandmother with a pair of startling eyes, and then, turning, made a rush for the door. But her father was too quick for her. He closed it with a laugh, and stood with his back to it. The child did not cry, but, with flaming cheeks, she began to beat her father's knees with her small fists.</p>
<p n="ENG19090423">“Go and kiss granny, darling,” said Roger, stroking her dark head.</p>
<p n="ENG19090424">Beatty turned again, put both her hands behind her, and stood immovable.</p>
<p n="ENG19090425">“Not kiss granny,” she said firmly. “Don't love granny.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090426">“Oh, Beatty”—Mrs. French knelt down beside her—“come and be a good little girl, and I'll show you picture-books.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090427">“I not Beatty—I Jemima Ann,” said the small thin voice. “Not be a dood dirl—do upstairs.”</p>
<p n="ENG19090428">She looked at her father again, and then, evidently perceiving that he was not to be moved by force, she changed her tactics. Her delicate, elfish face melted into the sweetest smile; she stood on tiptoe, holding out to him her tiny arms. With a laugh of irrepressible pride and pleasure, Roger stooped to her and lifted her up. She nestled on his shoulder—a small odalisque, dark, lithe, and tawny, beside her handsome, fair-skinned father. And Roger's manner of holding and caressing her showed the passionate affection with which he regarded her.</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG1909069">“Then,” said Miss Floyd, smiling at the General, “let us go and sit in the garden, and feel ourselves aristocratic and superior.”</p>
<p n="ENG1909070">The General's brow smoothed. Voice and smile were alike engaging. Their owner was not exactly pretty, but she had very large dark eyes, and a small glowing face, set in a profusion of hair. Her neck, the General thought, was the slenderest he had ever seen, and the slight round lines of her form spoke of youth in its first delicate maturity. He followed her obediently, and they were all soon in the garden again, and free of the crowd. Miss Floyd led the way across the grass with the General.</p>
<p n="ENG1909071">“Ah! now you will see the General will begin to like us,” said Miss Boyson. “Daphne has got him in hand.”</p>
<p n="ENG1909072">Her tone was slightly mocking. Barnes observed the two figures in front of them, and remarked that Miss Floyd had a “very—well—a very foreign look.”</p>
<p n="ENG1909073">“Not English, you mean?—or American? Well, naturally. Her mother was a Spaniard—a South American—from Buenos Ayres. That's why she is so dark, and so graceful.”</p>
<p n="ENG1909074">“I never saw a prettier dress,” said Barnes, following the slight figure with his eyes. “It's so simple.”</p>
<p n="ENG1909075">His companion laughed again. The manner of the laugh puzzled her companion, but, just as he was about to put a question, the General and the young lady paused in front, to let the rest of the party come up with them. Miss Floyd proposed a seat a little way down the slope, where they might wait the half-hour appointed.</p>
<p n="ENG1909076">That half-hour passed quickly for all concerned. In looking back upon it afterwards two of the party were conscious that it had all hung upon one person. Daphne Floyd sat beside the General, who paid her a half-reluctant, half-fascinated attention. Without any apparent effort on her part she became indeed the centre of the group who sat or lay on the grass. All faces were turned towards her, and presently all ears listened for her remarks. Her talk was young and vivacious, nothing more. But all she said came, as it were, steeped in personality, a personality so energetic, so charged with movement and with action that it arrested the spectators—not always agreeably. It was like the passage of a train through the darkness, when, for the moment, the quietest landscape turns to fire and force.</p>
<p n="ENG1909077">The comparison suggested itself to Captain Boyson as he lay watching her, only to be received with an inward mockery, half bitter, half amused. This girl was always awakening in him these violent or desperate images. Was it her fault that she possessed those brilliant eyes—eyes, as it seemed, of the typical, essential woman?—and that downy brunette skin, with the tinge in it of damask red?—and that instinctive art of lovely gesture in which her whole being seemed to express itself? Boyson, who was not only a rising soldier, but an excellent amateur artist, knew every line of the face by heart. He had drawn Miss Daphne from the life on several occasions; and from memory scores of times. He was not likely to draw her from life any more; and thereby hung a tale. As far as he was concerned the train had passed—in flame and fury—leaving an echoing silence behind it.</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG190901039">“My sister and I introduced Daphne Floyd to Barnes,” he said steadily, “and it is my country, as I hold—or a portion of it—that allows these villainies. Some day we shall get a great reaction in the States, and then the reforms that plenty of us are clamouring for will come about. Meanwhile, as of course you know”—he addressed French—“New Yorkers and Bostonians suffer almost as much from the abominations that Nevada and South Dakota call laws, as Barnes has suffered. Marriage in the eastern States is as sacred as with you—South Carolina allows no divorce at all—but with this licence at our gates, no one is safe, and thousands of our women, in particular—for the women bring two-thirds of the actions—are going to the deuce, simply because they have the opportunity of going. And the children—it doesn't bear thinking of! Well—no good haranguing! I'm ashamed of my country in this matter—I have been for a long time—and I mean to help Barnes out, coûte que coûte! And as to the money, Barnes, you and I'll discuss that.”</p>
<p n="ENG190901040">Barnes lifted a face that quivered, and he and Boyson exchanged looks.</p>
<p n="ENG190901041">Penrose glanced at the pair. That imaginative power, combined with the power of drudgery, which was in process of making a great lawyer out of a Balliol scholar, showed him something typical and dramatic in the two figures:—in Boyson, on the one hand, so lithe, serviceable, and resolved, a helpful, mercurial man, ashamed of his country in this one respect, because he adored her in so many others, penitent and patriot in one:—in Barnes, on the other, so heavy, inert, and bewildered, a shipwrecked suppliant as it were, clinging to the knees of that very America which had so lightly and irresponsibly wronged him.</p>
<p n="ENG190901042">It was Penrose who broke the silence.</p>
<p n="ENG190901043">“Is there any chance of Mrs. Barnes's marrying again?” he asked.</p>
<p n="ENG190901044">Barnes turned to him.</p>
<p n="ENG190901045">“Not that I know of.”</p>
<p n="ENG190901046">“There's no one else in the case?”</p>
<p n="ENG190901047">“I never heard of anyone.” Roger gave a short, excited laugh. “What she's done, she's done because she was tired of me, not because she was in love with anyone else. That was her great score in the divorce case—that there was nobody.”</p>
<p n="ENG190901048">Biting and twisting his lip, in a trick that recalled to French the beautiful Eton lad, cracking his brains in the pupil-room over a bit of Latin prose, Roger glanced, frowning, from one to the other of these three men who felt for him, whose resentment of the wrong that had been done him, whose pity for his calamity showed plainly enough through their reticent speech.</p>
</sample></samples>