<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<samples n="ENG19080">
<sample><p n="ENG19080337">The men were eating as they talked, and even in this they were typical. Dr. Bull and the Marquis ate casually and conventionally of the best things on the table—cold pheasant or Strasbourg pie. But the Secretary was a vegetarian, and he spoke earnestly of the projected murder over half a raw tomato and three quarters of a glass of tepid water. The old Professor had such slops as suggested a sickening second childhood. And even in this President Sunday preserved his curious predominance of mere mass. For he ate like twenty men; he ate incredibly, with a frightful freshness of appetite, so that it was like watching a sausage factory. Yet continually, when he had swallowed a dozen crumpets or drunk a quart of coffee, he would be found with his great head on one side staring at Syme.</p>
<p n="ENG19080338">“I have often wondered,” said the Marquis, taking a great bite out of a slice of bread and jam, “whether it wouldn’t be better for me to do it with a knife. Most of the best things have been brought off with a knife. And it would be a new emotion to get a knife into a French President and wriggle it round.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080339">“You are wrong,” said the Secretary, drawing his black brows together. “The knife was merely the expression of the old personal quarrel with a personal tyrant. Dynamite is not only our best tool, but our best symbol. It is as perfect a symbol of us as is incense of the prayers of the Christians. It expands; it only destroys because it broadens; even so, thought only destroys because it broadens. A man’s brain is a bomb,” he cried out, loosening suddenly his strange passion and striking his own skull with violence. “My brain feels like a bomb, night and day. It must expand! It must expand! A man’s brain must expand, if it breaks up the universe.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080340">“I don’t want the universe broken up just yet,” drawled the Marquis. “I want to do a lot of beastly things before I die. I thought of one yesterday in bed.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080341">“No, if the only end of the thing is nothing,” said Dr. Bull with his sphinx-like smile, “it hardly seems worth doing.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080342">The old Professor was staring at the ceiling with dull eyes.</p>
<p n="ENG19080343">“Every man knows in his heart, ” he said, “that nothing is worth doing.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080344">There was a singular silence, and then the Secretary said—</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG190801238">And then Gogol said, with the absolute simplicity of a child—</p>
<p n="ENG190801239">“I wish I knew why I was hurt so much.”</p>
<p n="ENG190801240">Still Sunday said nothing, but only sat with his mighty chin upon his hand, and gazed at the distance. Then at last he said—</p>
<p n="ENG190801241">“I have heard your complaints in order. And here, I think, comes another to complain, and we will hear him also.”</p>
<p n="ENG190801242">The falling fire in the great cresset threw a last long gleam, like a bar of burning gold, across the dim grass. Against this fiery band was outlined in utter black the advancing legs of a black‑clad figure. He seemed to have a fine close suit with knee‑breeches such as that which was worn by the servants of the house, only that it was not blue, but of this absolute sable. He had, like the servants, a kind of word by his side. It was only when he had come quite close to the crescent of the seven and flung up his face to look at them, that Syme saw, with thunder‑struck clearness, that the face was the broad, almost ape‑like face of his old friend Gregory, with its rank red hair and its insulting smile.</p>
<p n="ENG190801243">“Gregory!” gasped Syme, half‑rising from his seat. “Why, this is the real anarchist!”</p>
<p n="ENG190801244">“Yes,” said Gregory, with a great and dangerous restraint, “I am the real anarchist.”</p>
<p n="ENG190801245">“ ‘Now there was a day,’ ” murmured Bull, who seemed really to have fallen asleep, ” ‘when the sons of God came to present themselves before the Lord, and Satan came also among them.’ ”</p>
<p n="ENG190801246">“You are right,” said Gregory, and gazed all round. “I am a destroyer. I would destroy the world if I could.”</p>
<p n="ENG190801247">A sense of a pathos far under the earth stirred up in Syme, and he spoke brokenly and without sequence.</p>
<p n="ENG190801248">“Oh, most unhappy man,” he cried, “try to be happy! You have red hair like your sister.”</p>
<p n="ENG190801249">“My red hair, like red flames, shall burn up the world,” said Gregory. “I thought I hated everything more than common men can hate anything; but I find that I do not hate everything so much as I hate you! ”</p>
<p n="ENG190801250">“I never hated you,” said Syme very sadly.</p>
<p n="ENG190801251">Then out of this unintelligible creature the last thunders broke.</p>
<p n="ENG190801252">“You! ” he cried. “You never hated because you never lived. I know what you are all of you, from first to last—you are the people in power! You are the police—the great fat, smiling men in blue and buttons! You are the Law, and you have never been broken. But is there a free soul alive that does not long to break you, only because you have never been broken? We in revolt talk all kind of nonsense doubtless about this crime or that crime of the Government. It is all folly! The only crime of the Government is that it governs. The unpardonable sin of the supreme power is that it is supreme. I do not curse you for being cruel. I do not curse you (though I might) for being kind. I curse you for being safe! You sit in your chairs of stone, and have never come down from them. You are the seven angels of heaven, and you have had no troubles. Oh, I could forgive you everything, you that rule all mankind, if I could feel for once that you had suffered for one hour a real agony such as I—”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG19080191">“Comrades!” he cried, in a voice that made every man jump out of his boots, “have we come here for this? Do we live underground like rats in order to listen to talk like this? This is talk we might listen to while eating buns at a Sunday School treat. Do we line these walls with weapons and bar that door with death lest anyone should come and hear Comrade Gregory saying to us, ‘Be good, and you will be happy,’ ‘Honesty is the best policy,’ and ‘Virtue is its own reward’? There was not a word in Comrade Gregory’s address to which a curate could not have listened with pleasure (hear, hear). But I am not a curate (loud cheers), and I did not listen to it with pleasure (renewed cheers). The man who is fitted to make a good curate is not fitted to make a resolute, forcible, and efficient Thursday (hear, hear).”</p>
<p n="ENG19080192">“Comrade Gregory has told us, in only too apologetic a tone, that we are not the enemies of society. But I say that we are the enemies of society, and so much the worse for society. We are the enemies of society, for society is the enemy of humanity, its oldest and its most pitiless enemy (hear, hear). Comrade Gregory has told us (apologetically again) that we are not murderers. There I agree. We are not murderers, we are executioners (cheers).”</p>
<p n="ENG19080193">Ever since Syme had risen Gregory had sat staring at him, his face idiotic with astonishment. Now in the pause his lips of clay parted, and he said, with an automatic and lifeless distinctness—</p>
<p n="ENG19080194">“You damnable hypocrite!”</p>
<p n="ENG19080195">Syme looked straight into those frightful eyes with his own pale blue ones, and said with dignity—</p>
<p n="ENG19080196">“Comrade Gregory accuses me of hypocrisy. He knows as well as I do that I am keeping all my engagements and doing nothing but my duty. I do not mince words. I do not pretend to. I say that Comrade Gregory is unfit to be Thursday for all his amiable qualities. He is unfit to be Thursday because of his amiable qualities. We do not want the Supreme Council of Anarchy in­fected with a maudlin mercy (hear, hear). This is no time for ceremonial politeness, neither is it a time for ceremonial modesty. I set myself against Comrade Gregory as I would set myself against all the Governments of Europe, because the anarchist who has given himself to anarchy has forgotten modesty as much as he has forgotten pride (cheers). I am not a man at all. I am a cause (renewed cheers). I set myself against Comrade Gregory as impersonally and as calmly as I should choose one pistol rather than another out of that rack upon the wall; and I say that rather than have Gregory and his milk‑and‑water methods on the Supreme Council, I would offer myself for election—”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG19080500">“We are too late,” he said, “the hygienic Doctor has gone to bed.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080501">“What do you mean?” asked Syme. “Does he live over there, then?”</p>
<p n="ENG19080502">“Yes,” said de Worms, “behind that particular window which you can’t see. Come along and get some dinner. We must call on him to‑morrow morning.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080503">Without further parley, he led the way through several by‑ways until they came out into the flare and clamour of the East India Dock Road. The Professor, who seemed to know his way about the neighbourhood, proceeded to a place where the line of lighted shops fell back into a sort of abrupt twilight and quiet, in which an old white inn, all out of repair, stood back some twenty feet from the road.</p>
<p n="ENG19080504">“You can find good English inns left by accident everywhere, like fossils,” explained the Professor. “I once found a decent place in the West End.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080505">“I suppose,” said Syme, smiling, “that this is the corresponding decent place in the East End?”</p>
<p n="ENG19080506">“It is,” said the Professor reverently, and went in.</p>
<p n="ENG19080507">In that place they dined and slept, both very thoroughly. The beans and bacon, which these unaccountable people cooked well, the astonishing emergence of Burgundy from their cellars, crowned Syme’s sense of a new comradeship and comfort. Through all this ordeal his root horror had been isolation, and there are no words to express the abyss between isolation and having one ally. It may be conceded to the mathematicians that four is twice two. But two is not twice one; two is two thousand times one. That is why, in spite of a hundred disadvantages, the world will always return to monogamy.</p>
<p n="ENG19080508">Syme was able to pour out for the first time the whole of his outrageous tale, from the time when Gregory had taken him to the little tavern by the river. He did it idly and amply, in a luxuriant monologue, as a man speaks with very old friends. On his side, also, the man who had impersonated Professor de Worms was not less communicative. His own story was almost as silly as Syme’s.</p>
<p n="ENG19080509">“That’s a good get‑up of yours,” said Syme, draining a glass of Mâcon; “a lot better than old Gogol’s. Even at the start I thought he was a bit too hairy.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080510">“A difference of artistic theory,” replied the Professor pensively. “Gogol was an idealist. He made up as the abstract or platonic ideal of an anarchist. But I am a realist. I am a portrait painter. But, indeed, to say that I am a portrait painter is an inadequate expression. I am a portrait.”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG19080766">“With the people out of that train,” said the other.</p>
<p n="ENG19080767">“What you say seems utterly wild,” began Syme. “Why, as a matter of fact—But, my God,” he cried out suddenly, like a man who sees an explosion a long way off, “by God! if this is true the whole bally lot of us on the Anarchist Council were against anarchy! Every born man was a detective except the President and his personal secretary. What can it mean?”</p>
<p n="ENG19080768">“Mean!” said the new policeman with incredible violence. “It means that we are struck dead! Don’t you know Sunday? Don’t you know that his jokes are always so big and simple that one has never thought of them? Can you think of anything more like Sunday than this, that he should put all his powerful enemies on the Supreme Council, and then take care that it was not supreme? I tell you he has bought every trust, he has captured every cable, he has control of every railway line—especially of that railway line!” and he pointed a shaking finger towards the small wayside station. “The whole movement was controlled by him; half the world was ready to rise for him. But there were just five people, perhaps, who would have resisted him . . . and the old devil put them on the Supreme Council, to waste their time in watching each other. Idiots that we are, he planned the whole of our idiocies! Sunday knew that the Professor would chase Syme through London, and that Syme would fight me in France. And he was combining great masses of capital, and seizing great lines of telegraphy, while we five idiots were running after each other like a lot of confounded babies playing blind man’s buff.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080769">“Well?” asked Syme with a sort of steadiness.</p>
<p n="ENG19080770">“Well,” replied the other with sudden serenity, “he has found us playing blind man’s buff to‑day in a field of great rustic beauty and extreme solitude. He has probably captured the world; it only remains to him to capture this field and all the fools in it. And since you really want to know what was my objection to the arrival of that train, I will tell you. My objection was that Sunday or his Secretary has just this moment got out of it.”</p>
<p n="ENG19080771">Syme uttered an involuntary cry, and they all turned their eyes towards the far‑off station. It was quite true that a considerable bulk of people seemed to be moving in their direction. But they were too distant to be dis­tinguished in any way.</p>
</sample></samples>