<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<samples n="ENG19060">
<sample><p n="ENG19060903">“I shouldn’t think so. But we might try.”</p>
<p n="ENG19060904">So they tried. But the blank silence of the damp dungeon remained unchanged.</p>
<p n="ENG19060905">“What was the name the Queen said?” asked Cyril suddenly. “Nisbeth—Nesbit—something? You know, the slave of the great names?”</p>
<p n="ENG19060906">“Wait a sec,” said Robert, “though I don’t know why you want it. Nusroch—Nisrock—Nisroch—That’s it.”</p>
<p n="ENG19060907">Then Anthea pulled herself together. All her muscles tightened, and the muscles of her mind and soul, if you can call them that, tightened too.</p>
<p n="ENG19060908">“UR‐HEKAU SETCHEH,” she cried in a fervent voice. “Oh, Nisroch, servant of the Great Ones, come and help us!”</p>
<p n="ENG19060909">There was a waiting silence. Then a cold, blue light awoke in the corner where the straw was—and in the light they saw coming towards them a strange and terrible figure. I won’t try to describe it, because Mr. Millar will draw it for you, exactly as it was, and exactly as the old Babylonians carved it on their stones, so that you can see it in our own British Museum at this day. I will just say that it had eagle’s wings and an eagle’s head and the body of a man.</p>
<p n="ENG19060910">It came towards them, strong and unspeakably horrible.</p>
<p n="ENG19060911">“Oh, go away,” cried Anthea; but Cyril cried, “No; stay!”</p>
<p n="ENG19060912">The creature hesitated, then bowed low before them on the damp floor of the dungeon.</p>
<p n="ENG19060913">“Speak,” it said, in a harsh, grating voice like large rusty keys being turned in locks. “the servant of the Great Ones is your servant. What is your need that you call on the name of Nisroch?”</p>
<p n="ENG19060914">“We want to go home,” said Robert.</p>
<p n="ENG19060915">“No, no,” cried Anthea; “we want to be where Jane is.”</p>
<p n="ENG19060916">Nisroch raised his great arm and pointed at the wall of the dungeon. And, as he pointed, the wall disappeared, and instead of the damp, green, rocky surface, there shone and glowed a room with rich hangings of red silk embroidered with golden water‐lilies, with cushioned couches and great mirrors of polished steel; and in it was the Queen, and before her, on a red pillow, sat the Psammead, its fur hunched up in an irritated, discontented way. On a blue‐covered couch lay Jane fast asleep.</p>
<p n="ENG19060917">“Walk forward without fear,” said Nisroch. “Is there aught else that the Servant of the great Name can do for those who speak that name?”</p>
<p n="ENG19060918">“No—oh, no,” said Cyril. “It’s all right now. Thanks ever so.”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG190601956">“Come!” she cried, “oh, come home! She may be dead before we get there, and then we can’t give it to her. Oh, come!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601957">“Ah, don’t let the dream end now!” pleaded the learned gentleman.</p>
<p n="ENG190601958">“It must,” said Anthea firmly, and kissed him again.</p>
<p n="ENG190601959">“When it comes to people dying,” said Robert, “good‐bye! I’m so glad you’re rich and famous and happy.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601960">“Do come!” cried Jane, stamping in her agony of impatience.</p>
<p n="ENG190601961">And they went. Old Nurse brought in tea almost as soon as they were back in Fitzroy Street. As she came in with the tray, the girls rushed at her and nearly upset her and it.</p>
<p n="ENG190601962">“Don’t die!” cried Jane, “oh, don’t!” and Anthea cried, “Dear, ducky, darling old Nurse, don’t die!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601963">“Lord, love you!” said Nurse, “I’m not agoing to die yet a while, please Heaven! Whatever on earth’s the matter with the chicks?”</p>
<p n="ENG190601964">“Nothing. Only don’t!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601965">She put the tray down and hugged the girls in turn. The boys thumped her on the back with heartfelt affection.</p>
<p n="ENG190601966">“I’m as well as ever I was in my life,” she said. “What nonsense about dying! You’ve been a setting too long in the dusk, that’s what it is. Regular blind man’s holiday. Leave go of me, while I light the gas.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601967">The yellow light illuminated four pale faces.</p>
<p n="ENG190601968">“We do love you so,” Anthea went on, “and we’ve made you a picture to show you how we love you. Get it out, Squirrel.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601969">The glazed testimonial was dragged out from under the sofa and displayed.</p>
<p n="ENG190601970">“The glue’s not dry yet,” said Cyril, “look out!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601971">“What a beauty!” cried old Nurse. “Well, I never! And your pictures and the beautiful writing and all. Well, I always did say your hearts was in the right place, if a bit careless at times. Well! I never did! I don’t know as I was ever pleased better in my life.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601972">She hugged them all, one after the other. And the boys did not mind it, somehow, that day.</p>
<p n="ENG190601973">“How is it we can remember all about the future, now?” Anthea woke the Psammead with laborious gentleness to put the question. “How is it we can remember what we saw in the future, and yet, when we were in the future, we could not remember the bit of the future that was past then, the time of finding the Amulet?”</p>
<p n="ENG190601974">“Why, what a silly question!” said the Psammead, “of course you cannot remember what hasn’t happened yet.”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG19060368">“We’ve got to go on with it,” said Anthea, “and as the eldest has to go first, you’ll have to be last, Jane. You quite understand about holding on to the charm as you go through, don’t you, Pussy?”</p>
<p n="ENG19060369">“I wish I hadn’t got to be last,” said Jane.</p>
<p n="ENG19060370">“You shall carry the Psammead if you like,” said Anthea. “That is,” she added, remembering the beast’s queer temper, “if it’ll let you.”</p>
<p n="ENG19060371">The Psammead, however, was unexpectedly amiable.</p>
<p n="ENG19060372">“I don’t mind,” it said, “who carries me, so long as it doesn’t drop me. I can’t bear being dropped.”</p>
<p n="ENG19060373">Jane with trembling hands took the Psammead and its fish‐basket under one arm. The charm’s long string was hung round her neck. Then they all stood up. Jane held out the charm at arm’s length, and Cyril solemnly pronounced the word of power.</p>
<p n="ENG19060374">As he spoke it the charm grew tall and broad, and he saw that Jane was just holding on to the edge of a great red arch of very curious shape. The opening of the arch was small, but Cyril saw that he could go through it. All round and beyond the arch were the faded trees and trampled grass of Regent’s Park, where the little ragged children were playing Ring o’ Roses. But through the opening of it shone a blaze of blue and yellow and red. Cyril drew a long breath and stiffened his legs so that the others should not see that his knees were trembling and almost knocking together. “Here goes!” he said, and, stepping up through the arch, disappeared. Then followed Anthea. Robert, coming next, held fast, at Anthea’s suggestion, to the sleeve of Jane, who was thus dragged safely through the arch. And as soon as they were on the other side of the arch there was no more arch at all and no more Regent’s Park either, only the charm in Jane’s hand, and it was its proper size again. They were now in a light so bright that they winked and blinked and rubbed their eyes. During this dazzling interval Anthea felt for the charm and pushed it inside Jane’s frock, so that it might be quite safe. When their eyes got used to the new wonderful light the children looked around them. The sky was very, very blue, and it sparkled and glittered and dazzled like the sea at home when the sun shines on it.</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG190601224">“Very well,” said the learned gentleman, now quite certain that he was dreaming.</p>
<p n="ENG190601225">Anthea held out her soft, pink hand. He took it. She pulled him gently to his feet. Jane held up the Amulet.</p>
<p n="ENG190601226">“To just outside Atlantis,” said Cyril, and Jane said the Name of Power.</p>
<p n="ENG190601227">“You owl!” said Robert, “it’s an island. Outside an island’s all water.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601228">“I won’t go. I won’t,” said the Psammead, kicking and struggling in its bag.</p>
<p n="ENG190601229">But already the Amulet had grown to a great arch. Cyril pushed the learned gentleman, as undoubtedly the first‐born, through the arch—not into water, but on to a wooden floor, out of doors. The others followed. The Amulet grew smaller again, and there they all were, standing on the deck of a ship whose sailors were busy making her fast with chains to rings on a white quay‐side. The rings and the chains were of a metal that shone red‐yellow like gold.</p>
<p n="ENG190601230">Every one on the ship seemed too busy at first to notice the group of newcomers from Fitzroy Street. Those who seemed to be officers were shouting orders to the men.</p>
<p n="ENG190601231">They stood and looked across the wide quay to the town that rose beyond it. What they saw was the most beautiful sight any of them had ever seen—or ever dreamed of.</p>
<p n="ENG190601232">The blue sea sparkled in soft sunlight; little white‐capped waves broke softly against the marble breakwaters that guarded the shipping of a great city from the wildness of winter winds and seas. The quay was of marble, white and sparkling with a veining bright as gold. The city was of marble, red and white. The greater buildings that seemed to be temples and palaces were roofed with what looked like gold and silver, but most of the roofs were of copper that glowed golden‐red on the houses on the hills among which the city stood, and shaded into marvellous tints of green and blue and purple where they had been touched by the salt sea spray and the fumes of the dyeing and smelting works of the lower town.</p>
<p n="ENG190601233">Broad and magnificent flights of marble stairs led up from the quay to a sort of terrace that seemed to run along for miles, and beyond rose the town built on a hill.</p>
<p n="ENG190601234">The learned gentleman drew a long breath. “Wonderful!” he said, “wonderful!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601235">“I say, Mr.—what’s your name,” said Robert.</p>
<p n="ENG190601236">“He means,” said Anthea, with gentle politeness, “that we never can remember your name. I know it’s Mr De Something.”</p>
</sample>
<sample><p n="ENG190601953">“Old Nurse dead?” said Anthea. “Oh, no!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601954">“Yes, yes, it’s the common lot. It’s a long time ago now.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601955">Jane held up the Amulet in a hand that twittered.</p>
<p n="ENG190601956">“Come!” she cried, “oh, come home! She may be dead before we get there, and then we can’t give it to her. Oh, come!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601957">“Ah, don’t let the dream end now!” pleaded the learned gentleman.</p>
<p n="ENG190601958">“It must,” said Anthea firmly, and kissed him again.</p>
<p n="ENG190601959">“When it comes to people dying,” said Robert, “good‐bye! I’m so glad you’re rich and famous and happy.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601960">“Do come!” cried Jane, stamping in her agony of impatience.</p>
<p n="ENG190601961">And they went. Old Nurse brought in tea almost as soon as they were back in Fitzroy Street. As she came in with the tray, the girls rushed at her and nearly upset her and it.</p>
<p n="ENG190601962">“Don’t die!” cried Jane, “oh, don’t!” and Anthea cried, “Dear, ducky, darling old Nurse, don’t die!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601963">“Lord, love you!” said Nurse, “I’m not agoing to die yet a while, please Heaven! Whatever on earth’s the matter with the chicks?”</p>
<p n="ENG190601964">“Nothing. Only don’t!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601965">She put the tray down and hugged the girls in turn. The boys thumped her on the back with heartfelt affection.</p>
<p n="ENG190601966">“I’m as well as ever I was in my life,” she said. “What nonsense about dying! You’ve been a setting too long in the dusk, that’s what it is. Regular blind man’s holiday. Leave go of me, while I light the gas.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601967">The yellow light illuminated four pale faces.</p>
<p n="ENG190601968">“We do love you so,” Anthea went on, “and we’ve made you a picture to show you how we love you. Get it out, Squirrel.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601969">The glazed testimonial was dragged out from under the sofa and displayed.</p>
<p n="ENG190601970">“The glue’s not dry yet,” said Cyril, “look out!”</p>
<p n="ENG190601971">“What a beauty!” cried old Nurse. “Well, I never! And your pictures and the beautiful writing and all. Well, I always did say your hearts was in the right place, if a bit careless at times. Well! I never did! I don’t know as I was ever pleased better in my life.”</p>
<p n="ENG190601972">She hugged them all, one after the other. And the boys did not mind it, somehow, that day.</p>
<p n="ENG190601973">“How is it we can remember all about the future, now?” Anthea woke the Psammead with laborious gentleness to put the question. “How is it we can remember what we saw in the future, and yet, when we were in the future, we could not remember the bit of the future that was past then, the time of finding the Amulet?”</p>
</sample></samples>